Guide to the Schepps/Brand Family Papers, 1910-1997 MS 843
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Schepps/Brand Family Papers
1910-1997
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Brand, Nancy
MS 843
2 Linear Feet 2 boxes
This collection is made up of two boxes containing awards and certificates, event materials, correspondence, photographs, publications, and newsclippings from the Schepps/Brand family, spanning from 1910-1997.
Biographical / Historical
Manet Davis Schepps was born in Houston, Texas, on February 22, 1917, to Bertha and Abe Davis. She grew up in Houston and attended San Jacinto High School, where she wrote for the newspaper, served as President of the Chi Comrades, which was a forerunner of B'nai B'rith Girls.
Alvin Schepps was born March 3, 1910 in Poland. He immigrated to the United State in 1913 through "The Galveston Plan." Schepps settled in Dallas with his parents, eight brothers, and two sisters. After graduating from Forest Avenue High in 1928, Schepps spent the next 4 years at Texas A&M where he earned a degree in chemical engineering and was commissioned into the army reserves. After graduation, he moved to Houston and formed Schepps Grocery Co.
Manet and Alvin met in 1935 and married the following year at Adath Yeshurun in Houston on June 14, 1936.
Still in the Army Reserves, Schepps was called to active duty in 1942 and spent the next 4 years in the Army. His duties in the army involved concerns with chemical warfare services. He landed in France on June 6, 1944, as part of Operation Overlord on D-Day, and during the Battle of the Bulge he was promoted to Lieutenant Colonel and was awarded the Silver Star.
While Alvin was away, Manet ran the business, and took care of the first two of the couple's children, Sonnie and Dennis. After the war ended, Alvin returned home where they welcomed two more children, Gilda and Nancy.
The Schepps were well known for their community service and many charitable donations which included Texas A&M, and Texas A&M Hillel Foundation. The couple was very involved with their synagogue, Congregation Beth Yeshurun. Mr. Schepps served at President of Congregation Beth Yeshurun in the 1950s and was Chairman of the Building Committee for the congregation's building on Beechnut. Manet served as President of Beth Yeshurun Sisterhood and received the Martha Lea Stein award for service from the congregation in 1999.
Manet died on March 29, 2008 and Alvin died September 10, 2009. Both are interred at Beth Yeshurun Cemetery in Houston.
Excerpted from https://www.findagrave.com/memorial/25635708/manet-evelyn-schepps And https://www.findagrave.com/memorial/45004895/alvin-issie-schepps
Scope and Contents
Two boxes containing awards and certificates, event materials, correspondence, photographs, publications, and newsclippings document the lives of the Schepps/Brand family from 1910-1997.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Nancy Brand donated the papers in October of 2019.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection have been arranged in six series as follows: Series I: Awards and Certificates; Series II: Event Materials; Series III: General; Series IV: Photographs; Series V: Publications; Series VI: Oversize
Index Terms
Subjects
Jews and Jewish life
Document Types
awards; photographs; clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence
Subjects (Persons)
Brand, Nancy
- Series I: Awards and Certificates
  - Manet Davis Schepps Certificates and Diplomas, 1931-1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alvin Schepps Certificates, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Alvin and Manet Schepps Plaque from Beth Yeshurun, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series II: Event Materials
  - Beth Yeshurun Day School Succot Service, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - First Annual Awards Dinner, Houston friends of The Jewish Theological Seminary of America, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Twilight in the Park Program honoring Hana and Arthur Ginzbarg (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series III: General
  - Guest Book from Manet Davis and Alvin Schepps' Wedding, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Jewish Theological Seminary of America Correspondence, 1968-1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Beth Yeshurun Cemetery Association By-Laws, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series IV: Photographs
  - Family Photos, 1919-1964 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Event Photos, 1962-1996 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - First Annual Awards Dinner, Houston Friends of The Jewish Theological Seminary of America Photographs, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Chi Comrades Group Photos, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series V: Publications
  - News Clippings, 1910-1997 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Herzl-Lite Newsletter, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Jewish Theological Seminary of America Bulletin, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Series VI: Oversize
  - Manet Davis Certificate of Confirmation (Adath Yeshurun), 1931 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Schepps Family Group Photo, n.d. (Box 2)
  - The Chi Comrades wall hanging (news clippings) (Map-drawer 237, Folder 3)